I gotta tell you, I don't like to toot my horn a whole lot, but I do think that I've done a great
자랑하고 싶진 않지만 이번 주 프로젝트는 정말
job with the project for this week, and I enjoyed it so much.
잘 해낸 것 같아요 정말 즐거웠어요
And it's running now and I love it.
지금은 잘 굴러가요 정말 좋네요
I absolutely love it, and I can't wait to get into it and show it to you.
정말 마음에 들어요 빨리 들어가서 보여드리고 싶네요 Get it
And let's start, as always with the introduction.
늘 그렇듯 소개부터 시작하죠
But very quickly we're going to get to code because that is where it's at this time.
아주 빨리 코드로 가보겠습니다 지금은 get it에 있으니까요
So we're going to go deeply into a gigantic I.
거대한 I로 깊이 들어갈 거예요
It's such a hot topic.
화제의 중심이죠
It's something that everyone can't get enough of right now.
Get it은 요즘 모두가 질리지 않는 거죠
And so it's worth it that we really go deep and get into it, and we use it as an opportunity to learn
그러니 깊이 파고들 가치가 있죠 LMS의 다양한 구성 요소에 대해
more and more about the different components of LMS that we've worked on already over the last seven
더 많이 배울 기회로 사용합니다 지난 7주 반 동안 이미 작업해온 것들이죠
So what we're going to be doing today is talking about agentic workflows, agent frameworks, and then
오늘 우리가 할 것은 에이전틱 워크플로, 에이전트 프레임워크 그리고 에이전트
we're going to build an agent framework.
프레임워크를 구축하는 거예요
We're going to do it today that is able to send push notifications with information about great deals
오늘 그걸 할 겁니다 푸시 알림을 보낼 수 있는 거죠 RSS 피드를 보고 찾은 훌륭한
that it finds based on looking at RSS feeds.
서비스에 대한 정보와 함께요
So it's really putting all the pieces together into a solution.
모든 조각을 하나로 합치는 거죠
So before we do that, let's just quickly talk about what what is what exactly is Agentic AI and agent
그 전에 간단히 얘길 좀 하죠 에이전트 인공지능과 에이전트 워크플로가
workflows and all of this.
정확히 뭐죠?
And I think the truthful answer is that it's one of these ambiguous terms that still emerging and somewhat
진실한 대답은 이 용어가 모호하다는 겁니다 지금도 여러 집단이
overused by different groups.
남용하고 있죠
So it's used to mean a number of different things.
여러 가지 의미로 쓰이죠
But I think if you take a step back and I did mention this when we touched on it briefly in a previous
하지만 한 걸음 물러나서 지난 주에도 잠깐 언급했지만 한 걸음
week, uh, but if you take a step back, you can think of the hallmarks, the key aspects of Agentic
물러나서 생각해 보면 에이전트 인공지능의 주요 특징인 특징들을 이 5가지
AI as having these five pieces to it.
요소로 구성할 수 있어요
And no doubt there are some things that some people say it's more than this, and some people will say
어떤 사람들은 더 많다고 하고 어떤 사람들은 less라고
it's less than this.
하죠
But I think that the these are the big five.
하지만 이 다섯 가지가 가장 중요하다고 생각해요
So first of all, an agentic solution is one that is able to take a larger problem, a more complex
에이전트 솔루션은 더 큰 문제, 더 복잡한 문제를 작은 조각으로
problem, and divide it down into smaller pieces that can be executed potentially by LMS and maybe just
나누는 겁니다 잠재적으로 LMS나 소프트웨어의 일반 비트로 실행할
by normal bits of software.
수 있는 거죠
But that ability to take a harder task and break it down is certainly a hallmark of agent solutions.
하지만 어려운 작업을 분석하는 능력은 에이전트 솔루션의 특징이죠
The use of tools, function calling and structured outputs that we've covered at various points along
지금까지 다뤘던 도구 사용, 함수 호출, 구조화된 출력들을 살펴보죠
the way.
그것도 에이전트 솔루션의 소관 사항에 속하는 경우가 많죠
Is this idea that you're giving an LMS something that's more than just a conversational here's a prompt,
LMS에 단순한 대화 이상의 것을 주는 아이디어인가요? 채팅
give me back a chat response.
응답을 요청하세요
But it's something where it's fitting into a tighter construct.
하지만 더 탄탄한 구조에 맞아야 해요
We need outputs in this particular JSON format.
이 특정 JSON 포맷에서 출력이 필요해요
You can call these different functions to carry out different activities.
다른 활동을 수행하기 위해 이런 함수를 호출할 수 있어요
So that's how that fits into Agentic AI and environment.
에이전트식 인공지능과 환경에 그렇게 들어맞는 거죠
A framework environment.
프레임워크 환경이죠
The different words for it.
다른 단어들이요
But some kind of a of a of a sandbox in which, which provides some functionality which all the different
하지만 일종의 샌드박스 같은 것으로 모든 에이전트가 이용할 수 있는 기능성들을
agents would be able to take advantage of.
제공하죠
The classic example of this would be something like memory.
대표적인 예가 메모리 같은 거예요
If there's something where all of the agents can share in some bit of information that reflects what's
과거에 일어난 일을 반영하는 비트 정보를 모든 에이전트가 공유할 수 있는 그런
happened in the past or something like that, that would be an agent environment and just something
것이 있다면 그건 에이전트 환경이 되겠죠 다른 에이전트들이 어떤
which allows different agents to call each other in some way.
식으로든 서로 호출할 수 있도록 해주는 그런 거요
Uh, and then typically and again, this, this one is an example of something which isn't a must have.
그리고 전형적으로, 다시 말씀드리지만 이건 꼭 필요한 건 아닌 예시예요
It's not like without this you don't have an agent solution.
이게 없으면 에이전트 해결책이 없는 게 아니에요
But you often see agent solutions having a planning agent, an agent that's responsible for figuring
에이전트 솔루션에는 기획 에이전트가 있는 경우가 종종 있습니다 어떤 순서로 어떤
out what tasks to do in what order.
작업을 할지 결정하는 책임자죠
And again, I think normally when people talk about this, they're thinking of that planning agent being
일반적으로 사람들이 이에 대해 얘기할 때 기획 에이전트 그 자체가 LLM이라고
itself an LLM that's able to take a task and figure out, all right, I want to do this and then this
생각하죠 작업을 받아 알아낼 수 있는 거죠 이렇게 하고 저렇게 하고 이렇게 하는
and then this.
거요
But it doesn't have to be an LLM this.
LLM이 아니어도 돼요
If it's a simple problem that just has five steps to it or something, then you can just write some
간단한 문제이고 5단계 정도만 있다면 파이썬 코드를 작성해서
Python code that calls those steps, or it can be a JSON configuration file or something.
그 단계를 호출하거나 JSON 구성 파일을 만들면 돼요
But there's got to be something which is considered your, your, your planner to tick this box and
하지만 여러분의 플래너로 간주되는 뭔가가 있어야만 해요 이 박스에 체크할
not that it's necessarily required, but perhaps the last one here, which is the one that we've not
수 있도록요 꼭 필요한 건 아니지만요 여기 마지막 건 지금까지 별로
really done much of to date, is the kind of key.
다루지 않은 건데 일종의 핵심이죠
It's perhaps a single criterion that does distinguish between something that's agentic and it is not,
상징적인 것과 그렇지 않은 것을 구분하는 단 하나의 기준은
and that is autonomy.
바로 자율성이에요
That is this idea that your agentic AI solution has some kind of a existence that transcends a chat
그게 당신의 인공지능 솔루션이 인간과 대화하는 걸 초월하는 존재라는 생각이죠
So we've we've had memory before because we've had Q&amp;A chats like our Rag solution when we when we had
메모리를 본 적이 있어요 래그 솔루션 같은 Q&amp;A 채팅을 했거든요 보험 회사에
a chat that talked about the insurance company and obviously it had memory there, and we've had other
대해 얘기할 때요 당연히 메모리가 있었죠 다른 예제도 있었어요
Even our airline chat had memory, but that's not really considered an autonomous AI because that.
항공사 채팅도 메모리가 있었지만 그건 자율 인공지능이라고 볼 수 없어요
Memory only existed where we had that app running and while the human was interacting with it.
메모리는 앱이 실행되고 사람이 상호 작용할 때만 존재했어요
It didn't really have any kind of a of a presence beyond that.
그 외에는 어떤 존재감도 없었어요
So this idea of autonomy is some.
자율성이라는 개념은 일부에 불과해요
And some kind of a sense that this, this thing has an existence that is more permanent and.
그리고 이 생명체가 더 영구적으로 존재할 거라는 느낌도 들고요
Say, is running behind the scenes.
무대 뒤에서 달리고 있어요
Now, that might all sound a bit magical, and it's not at all.
비트가 마법처럼 들리겠지만 전혀 그렇지 않아요
As you'll see, basically, if you've got a process that's running, that's carrying out some activity.
보다시피 기본적으로 실행 중인 프로세스가 있다면 일부 활동을 수행하는 거죠
That doesn't necessarily need human interaction, that in itself is good enough to say, okay.
인간의 상호 작용이 꼭 필요한 건 아니에요 그것만으로도 충분하죠
That sounds like that's an agent solution.
에이전트 해결책 같네요
So in a nutshell, it's not like there's one super clear.
간단히 말해서 아주 명확한 건 없어요
Definition.
정의요
And a lot of the times when you're working with an AI solution that is solving a harder problem involving
인공지능 솔루션을 사용할 때 더 어려운 문제를 해결하는 경우가
multiple models Involving coordination between them and in a way that isn't just a prompt and a response.
많습니다 여러 모델이 조화를 이루는 문제인데 즉각적인 대응이 아니죠
The chat interface that we're so familiar with, anything like that is considered an agentic AI solution.
우리가 잘 아는 채팅 인터페이스는 에이전트식 인공지능 솔루션이에요
Now there are a bunch of frameworks which offer agent capabilities.
에이전트 기능을 제공하는 프레임워크가 많아요
Langshan has a bunch of agent abilities.
랑산은 대리인으로서 능력이 뛰어나요
There's agent tools that you get with hugging face.
요원들을 끌어안으면 Get it이 가능해요
Gradio has something and there's many others.
그라디오는 다른 것도 많이 갖고 있어요
Some of them are what they call no code.
어떤 건 코드도 없어요
So all you're doing is stitching together different, different models.
다양한 모델을 꿰매기만 하면 돼요
Some of them are have more code involved, like like a Lang Chain's offerings.
일부는 코드가 더 많이 포함돼 있어요 랭 체인에서 제공하는 것처럼요
But one of the points I wanted to make to you is that many of these platforms are putting on abstractions
여러분께 말씀드리고 싶은 것 중 하나는 이런 플랫폼 대부분이 옐름스의
around Llms, much as Lang Chain did for Rag when we came across that before.
추상화에 있다는 겁니다 랭 체인이 전에 Rag에 대해 했던 것처럼요
And really to be building these kinds of agentic AI solutions, you don't need those abstractions.
에이전트식 인공지능 솔루션을 구축하는 건 그런 추상화가 필요 없어요
We know how to call Llms directly and we can just do it ourselves.
`Lms'에 직접 전화하는 법을 아니까 우리가 직접 하면 돼요
We can have LMS running and we can send the right information to the right.
LMS가 실행되도록 할 수도 있고 올바른 정보를 올바른 곳으로 보낼 수도 있죠
LM as now a master of LM engineering, almost 5% away from being a master of LM engineering.
달 착륙선은 이제 달 착륙선 공학의 달인이 되었습니다 달 착륙선 공학의 달인이 되기까지 5% 가까이 남은 거죠
That's well within your capabilities.
당신 능력 안에서요
So actually for for this session, as we get in and build our Agentic AI framework, we're just going
이 세션에선 에이전틱 인공지능 프레임워크를 구축할 텐데요 에이전트를 생성하는
to be creating these agents, as you already saw those classes and have them operating ourselves using
걸 보겠습니다 이미 보신 클래스들이죠 파이썬 코드로 운영하는 거예요
We're going to collaborate them, stitch them together with our own code, which is a great way of doing
우리가 만든 코드로 조합해서 함께 만들 거예요 아주 좋은 방법이죠
it, and which also gives you deeper insight into what's happening.
무슨 일이 일어나는지 더 잘 알 수 있고요
And we can actually see what information is being passed between the agents.
요원들 사이에 어떤 정보가 오가는지 볼 수 있어요
Um, but of course, you can also use one of the more off the shelf, uh, more abstraction layer products.
물론 규격화된 걸 사용할 수도 있어요 더 추상화 층 제품요
If you wish.
원하신다면요
You can you can look up any of the ones that's available from, from Langshan or the others.
랑산이나 다른 데서 구할 수 있는 건 다 찾아봐요
Um, and it might be an interesting exercise to then redo some of what we're doing.
지금 하는 걸 다시 하는 것도 재미있을 것 같아요
It was it would probably be quite, quite straightforward to do it using one of those off the shelf
기성품으로 만드는 게 훨씬 더 쉬울 거예요
But for us, we're going to get to the nitty gritty.
Get it의 핵심으로 들어갈 거예요
We're actually going to go and build our own little agent framework and have multiple llms participate
우리만의 에이전트 프레임워크를 구축하고 여러 개의 llms가
in solving the problem that, you know, we're setting out to solve, which is scraping for for good
문제를 해결하는 데 참여하게 할 겁니다 인터넷에서 좋은 거래를 찾아내고 찾으면
deals on the internet and messaging us when it finds them.
메시지를 보내는 거죠
Let's remind ourselves quickly of what that framework looks like.
프레임워크가 어떻게 생겼는지 잠깐 되짚어보죠
What is our architecture?
우리 건축물은 뭘까요?
This is the the the workflows that we're putting together.
이게 우리가 만들고 있는 워크플로예요
Um, we have the three models that are running and an ensemble agent that calls them.
모델 3대가 운영 중이고 앙상블 에이전트가 모델에게 연락해요
This is an example of perhaps a bit of a stretch, because an ensemble model that calls other models
이건 비트를 좀 늘린 예라고 할 수 있죠 다른 모델에게 연락하는 앙상블 모델은 당나귀가
is something that's been around for donkeys years.
나온 지 오래됐거든요
People haven't called that Agentic AI in the past, but since we do have these running as separate classes
에이전트 인공지능이라고 불린 적은 없지만 이것들은 독립된 클래스로서 실행되고 있고 동일한
in their own right that have the same construct and the same ability as you'll see to log and to be
구조와 기능을 가지고 있습니다 프레임워크에 로그인하고 참여하는 것과 동일합니다
participating in this framework, it kind of makes sense to think of these as separate agents in their
이것들을 독립된 에이전트로 생각하는 것이 합리적입니다 원한다면 파이썬
own right, and we could be running them in different Python processes if we wish to.
프로세스에서 실행할 수도 있고요
But for simplicity, I just have it just be being called directly, but we certainly could do.
간단히 말하자면 그냥 직접 호출하는 거죠 그렇게 할 수도 있어요
Um, so I have chosen to suggest that these are separate agents that carry out these three different
그래서 저는 이 세 가지 에이전트가 각각 다른 세 가지 모델을 수행한다고
models, and that we have an ensemble agent that calls each of these agents, collaborates with them,
제안했어요 그리고 앙상블 에이전트가 각각의 에이전트를 호출해서
and then applies the linear regression weights to give an ensemble of a price of a product.
협업하게 한 다음 선형 회귀 추를 적용해서 제품의 가격을 매기는 거죠
The scanner agent is what we looked at last time.
스캐너 요원은 지난번에 봤던 거예요
This is an agent.
이 사람은 에이전트예요
We ended it by by calling the scanner agent.
스캐너 에이전트를 부르며 끝냈어요
It's able to go out, collect feeds, and then call Gpt4 zero as its way of finding out the good pithy
나가서 피드를 수집하고 Gpt4 0을 호출할 수 있습니다 각 거래에 대한 간결한 설명과 관련된
description of each deal and the price point associated with it.
가격점을 찾는 방법으로요
And it collects that together.
그게 한데 모이죠
And you may remember that it had an input memory, which is part of the glue of how we're going to glue
입력 메모리가 있었던 걸 기억하실 겁니다 모든 걸 하나로 붙이는 접착제의
everything together.
일부죠
The memory is where we tell it not to surface a deal, that it's already surfaced in the past.
이미 드러난 거래를 드러내지 말라고 메모리를 통해 말하죠
And what we're going to look at today are these boxes in yellow that bring it all together, that we're
오늘 살펴볼 것은 모두 함께 가져오는 이 노란 상자입니다 메시징 에이전트를
going to look at a messaging agent, a very simple thing that's going to send push notifications to
살펴볼 건데요 여러분 폰으로 푸시 알림을 보내는 아주 간단한 거죠
your phone, which is going to be delightful.
아주 근사할 거예요
A planning agent which is able to coordinate activities.
활동을 조정할 수 있는 기획 기획 요원이죠
And it's not going to be an LM, it's going to be a simple Python script, but it easily could be an
LM이 되지는 않을 겁니다 간단한 파이썬 스크립트가 될 겁니다 하지만 쉽게 LM이
LM.
될 수 있죠
And then the agent framework, which sounds super fancy.
에이전트 프레임워크도 있는데 엄청 고급스럽게 들리네요
Uh, it's not fancy in the least.
전혀 화려하지 않아요
It's just simply something which has all of these agents and which can allow messaging to go on.
단순히 이 모든 에이전트가 있고 메시지가 계속되게 해주는 거죠
And that's going to be our agent framework creation today.
그게 오늘날의 에이전트 프레임워크 생성이죠
And then tomorrow we're going to build the user interface that that wraps it all together and makes
내일은 사용자 인터페이스를 만들 겁니다 모든 걸 멋지게 감싸줄
it look fabulous.
인터페이스요
But I hopefully have motivated you enough to be ready to go.
하지만 동기가 충분해서 갈 준비가 됐길 바라요
I will see you in JupyterLab.
주피터랩에서 만나요